# **GAURAV MANDHYAN**

**B.Tech. Computer Science and Engineering** 

#### Professional Summary

Six years of overall IT experience including three years of Development and two years of being an IT Trainer / Group Lead.

### **Development ExperienceSummary**

- Purveyor of competitive intelligence and holistic, timely analyses of Big Data made possible by the successful installation, configuration of Hadoop ecosystem components and architecture.
- Capable of processing large sets of structured, semi-structured and unstructured data and supporting systems applicationarchitecture.
- VerygoodunderstandingondevelopingETLpipelineforvariouscustomersusingSpark,
  Scala. Hive and various Big data tools.
- Extensive experience in complete Software Development LifeCycle.
- Hands on experience of Spark Framework including Spark Core, SparkSQL and SparkStreamingwithScala.
- Hands on experience of Hadoop Framework like HDFS, YARN/MRV2, Hive, Pig, HBase, Impala, SqoopandHue.
- IndepthknowledgeandgoodunderstandingofHadoopdaemons:NameNode,DataNode, Secondary Name Node, Resource manager, Node Manager and HighAvailability.
- Hands on experience in CentOS andUbuntu.
- Provided support to development team in trouble shooting and performancetuning.
- Goodknowledgeonshellscripting.WorkedwithBigDatadistribution:Cloudera.
- Experience in the **Banking and Financial Services**domain.
- Able to craft complex shell scripts in order to develop automation of manual codereview.
- ResponsibleforprovidingTechnicalStandardsandComplianceapprovalorrejectiontothe application being on boarded onto the Client's Hadoop productionplatform.
- Co-ordinatedwithon-shoreteamandcross-functionalteamstoensurethatapplications are properly tested, configured anddeployed.
- InvolvedinAgileScrummethodologythatleveragesthe Clientbigdataplatformand used version control toolSVN.

#### IT Trainer Experience Summary

- Experience in management, handling and training of large groups of students and professionals as a part of dailyroutine.
- Involved in mentoring other Trainers to ensure optimum training standards for the organization.
- Co-ordinated with company owner and other stakeholders for discussions related to hiring team members, digital marketing and advertising and placement of trainees.
- Technologies covered throughout the years: Big Data and Analytics, Python with Data Exploration and Machine Learning, MATLAB, Shell Scripting, Core and Advance Java with Spring and Hibernate, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, JQuery, AngularJS, NodeJS, Android, DevOps.

### **Career Objective**

To work for continual progress and accuracy in diverse job responsibilities through continuous work and persistence. Seeking to utilize four years of IT experience in next challenging and rewarding position in customer focused IT, Finance or software organization.

### **Technical Skills Summary**

- BigDataEcosystems: Hadoop(CDH5.8.X), MapReduce, HDFS, HBase, Hive, ApachePig, Sqoop, Spark with Scala, UNIXShell
- Programming Languages: C, C++, Core Java, Python, Scala
- Scripting Languages: Bash,JS
- Databases: Oracle, SQL Server, MySQL
- Tools: Eclipse, NetBeans, PyCharm, AndroidStudio

#### **Professional Experience**

# Technical Head / Group Lead

NIIT Limited, Lucknow May 2018to Current

## Responsibilities:

- Involved in managing both the Technical and Accounts team at threecenters.
- Assigning work schedules, reviewing classroom training sessions, upskilling technical mentors, coordinating with higher management to promote education level across centers.
- Providing placement related guidance, conducting technical refresher, personality development skills and mock interview sessions for eligible candidates.
- Switchingamongdifferenttechnologies,upskillingselfandimpartingthesametoprovide an edge to both the Company and thestudents.

#### **Technical Mentor / IT Trainer**

NIIT Limited, Lucknow Dec 2015 to May 2018

### Responsibilities:

 Involvedindeliveringcontentandprojectbasedtrainingtoenrolledgraduateand undergraduate students as well asprofessionals.

/;Leading a team of Tech Mentors at one center, providing guidance, subject matter training,softskillsenhancementandpresentationtechniquesasapartoftheprocess.

 Conducting seminars, technical conferences, 'Tech-clinics' and KnowledgeTransition sessions for technical team.

# Big DataEngineer

Tata Consultancy Services, Noida Nov 2016 to Nov 2017

Domain: Payment and Transactions

Role: SoftwareDeveloper

# Responsibilities:

- Extensiveexperienceinanalyzing datausingHiveQLandchangingitaccordingtothe format required in DataLake.
- DevelopingETLpipelinetotransferthedailytransactiondatatoaCommonDataModel and finally exporting to required database servers(e.g Teradata), coming from various subsidiaries of client(PayPal).
- Automate all the repetitive tasks using Python

orBash.ManageddatacomingfromdifferentsourcesandinvolvedinHDFSmaintenancean d loading of structured and unstructureddata.

### **Hadoop Developer**

Tata Consultancy Services, Noida Feb 2015 to Oct 2015

Line of Business: Hadoop as aServiceDomain: Banking and FinancialServices

Role: Developer

### Responsibilities:

- WorkedonHadoopmigrationofETLprojectsextensivelytherebyutilizingtheHaaSplatformfor datawarehousing.
- Worked on ClouderaHadoop Distribution (CDH 5.8.3) platform to performHadoopoperations.
- Developed Simple to complex Map/reduceJobs.
- DevelopedHivetablestostoretheprocessedresultsinatabularformatandperformed transformations to make data suitable for loading into theDataWarehouse.
- Implemented external tables and dynamic partitions usingHive.
- Extensive knowledge on PIG scripts using bags andtuples.
- Involved in gathering the requirements, designing, development andtesting.
- Worked on Hue interface for querying thedata.
- Exported analyzed data to relational databases using Sqoop for visualization to generate reports for the BITeam.

## **Professional Awards & Accomplishments**

- WonAwardforautomatingthemanualtasks,savingthemanualeffortandimprovingefficiency of theteam.
- Delivery Excellence certificate awarded for successfully reviewing 40+ applications to been boarded onto the HaaSplatform.
- Had won Star Performer award and received TCS GEMS on countlessoccasions.
- 'StaroftheMonth'Awardforimplementingautomationscriptsthatsavealotoftimeand help completing task withinSLA.
- TCS'OntheSpot'Awardforimplementingbusinessrequirementsinshorttimespan.
- Knowledgebasecreationforinternaltraining, for various Hadooptools and concepts.
- Awarded 'Trainer of the year' and ranked first in Technical Group Discussion and Conference at NIITLucknow.

#### **Functional Skill Set**

- End to end responsible for the work itemsassigned.
- Cooperating and communicating with other team members for efficientworkmanagement.
- Solid analytical and troubleshooting skills. Ability to work in tight schedules and on different applicationsconcurrently.
- Excellent in communication, presentation and interpersonalskills.

### Personal Details

- DOB: 30th June, 1992
- Gender:Male
- Nationality:Indian
- Marital Status:Single
- Designation: SystemEngineer
- Location:Noida

# **Education**

■ B.Tech. in Computer Science andEngineering

Amity University, Lucknow, U.P. June 2009 to June 2014

High School &Intermediate

Stella Maris Inter College, Lucknow, U.P.